Yu'er
옥아
Come let the empress see you
이리 와서 황후마마께 인사 올리거라
How can this be?
어찌 이럴 수가
Right
옳소
How can he not follow orders?
어찌 명령을 무시하고
Rashly attack
막무가내로 진격한단 말이오
But he did win the battle after all
그래도 어찌 됐든 승전하지 않았소
Your Majesty arrives
폐하 납시오
Pay respects to Your Majesty
폐하를 뵙습니다
Let's all speak
말해보게
What's the matter?
무슨 일인가?
Your Majesty
폐하
I
소신
Wish to impeach Zhu Yuanzhi
주원지를 탄핵하려 합니다
Not long ago
얼마 전
Our Beishuo Army
우리 북삭군이
Engaged in close combat with Wuzhao's Shixin division
석랑이 이끈 오노군과 싸우게 되었는데
The Ministry of War ordered General Zhu
병부에서 적을 물리친 후
After repelling the enemy
주둔지로 퇴각하라고
To withdraw and defend the base
명하였으나
But General Zhu did not follow orders
주장군은 전령을 무시하고
Privately advanced recklessly
사사로이 진격하여
Actually pursued deep into Wuzhao territory
오노를 깊숙이 추격하여
Causing heavy losses to our troops
결국 아군이 심각한 손해를 보았습니다
And disrupted Your Majesty's approved battle plan
이는 폐하께서 정한 작전방침을
Completely
어지럽힌 행위입니다
But no matter what
어찌 됐든
General Zhu achieved a great victory this time
주 장군은 이번에 대승을 거두어
The entire southern Pingzhou
남부를 북삭군이
Was recovered by the Beishuo Army
전부 수복하였습니다
I think
저는 주 장군을
Not only should he not be punished
벌할 것이 아니라
But should be heavily rewarded
큰 상을 내려
To encourage the enterprising spirit of all
사람들의 진취심을 격려해야 한다고 봅니다
I remember
조정에서는 주 장군에게
The court only gave General Zhu
적을 물리칠 정도의 식량과
Supplies to repel the enemy
급료만 준 것 같은데
The money for his campaign
파병에 쓴 돈은
Where did it come from?
어디서 생긴 걸까요
This Zhu Yuanzhi
주원지가 땅을 차지하고
Is almost declaring himself king
왕이 되려나 봅니다
He uses
폐하를 위해
Your Majesty's land reform as a banner
토지 개혁을 추진한다는 명분으로
In Qingzhou
청주에서
Extensively seized land
함부로 토지를 징수하여
Directly distributed to the army
직접 군대에 나눠줬습니다
But General Zhu
하지만 주 장군은
Did successfully implement Your Majesty's new policies
폐하의 새로운 정책을 성공적으로 추진했습니다
This is a great merit
이 또한 큰 공로입니다
Forcibly seized from great families
세가와 토호들의 땅을 강제로 빼앗고
Privately divided court land
조정의 토지를 사사로이 나누는 것
This
이건
Is clearly
분명
Bandit behavior
비적 행세입니다
Alright, alright
됐네 그만하게
Stop arguing
이 일은
Let's put this matter aside for now
잠시 미루고
Discuss another day
다음에 논의하세
Court dismissed
이만 조회를 마치겠네
This phoenix
봉두가
Has gotten fat recently
근래 살이 쪘구나
It seems
범충이
Fan Zhong's meals are quite good
먹이를 잘 줬나 봐
Let's talk
말해 봐라
About General Zhu's matter
주 장군의 일을
What do you think?
어찌 처리하는 게 좋을까
Although General Zhu won a small victory
주 장군은 어렵게 승전했지만
He so flagrantly ignored court orders
조정의 명령을 철저히 무시했습니다
If something major happens in the future
만약 나중에 큰 일이 발생해도
And General Zhu still acts willfully
여전히 제멋대로 행동한다면
Cannot coordinate closely with the center
조정과 긴밀히 협력할 수 없어요
This would be a catastrophic hole
이건 상당히 위험합니다
Your son believes
절대 요행을
We cannot have wishful thinking
바라서는 안 되며
Should be punished
벌을 내려야 합니다
A general in the field
장수가 밖에 있다 보면
May not always follow the ruler's orders
어명을 못 지키는 경우도 있습니다
The battlefield changes in an instant
전세가 순식간에 변하는데
If everything follows central orders
사사건건 조정의 명령을 따르면
Then how do we seize opportunities?
어찌 전기를 잡겠습니까
Since ancient times
예로부터
Victory and defeat are decided in an instant
승부는 한순간에 가려졌습니다
Father
부황
Your son believes
소자가 봤을 때
General Zhu's intentions are correct
주 장군은 본심이 바르고
And he's brave and decisive
용맹하고 결단력이 있습니다
Should be rewarded
상을 내려야 합니다
Xuan shall prosper
선나라는 흥하라